优达学城 李开复专访
Udacity Talks with Kai-fu Lee
你好
Nihao.
真让人难以置信 我竟然能在北京的创新工厂
It is a unbelievable pleasure to be here in Beijing in Sinovation
碰到我一直以来的好友
with my good friend and long time friend
李开复博士
Dr. Kai-fu Lee.
我一直都很喜欢中国
I always love to be in China,
你也知道 中国估计是
because you know China is
当今最有创造力的国家
perhaps the most innovative country today.
全球的大科技公司
If you look at big Tech companies on the planet,
十个中有四个是中国人创办的
four out of ten are Chinese,
没有欧洲公司
there is no European company,
没有南美公司
there is no southern American company,
却有出色的中国公司
but there are amazing Chinese companies.
感谢开复
Thanks to Kai-fu,
开复是中国最具实力
whom I consider the most important
最有才华的投资者
and most talented investor in all China.
这永远是不平凡的一年的开始
This is always a fantastic start of a year;
就算是参观这里的新兴企业也能令人振奋
it is always great to visit start-up companies here.
我认为正是你们卓越的创新力和开拓力
I think you rival the Silicon Valley
使得你们能与硅谷匹敌
in your ability to innovate and build an amazing business.
我是这场对话的主持人
I'm here the moderator.
1991年我遇到了开复
I've met Kai-fu in 1991,
当时他在宾夕法尼亚州匹兹堡的
when he was in the faculty of a college in Pittsburgh
卡内基梅隆大学任教
of Pennsylvania called Carnegie Mellon University.
就在 5307 号
He was in 5307,
一个有窗户的办公室
a window office,
正好在我的无窗实验室旁边
right next to my windowless lab,
我当时在那里当旁听生
where I was acting as a visiting student.
开复是卡内基梅隆大学语音识别
Kai-fu was the preeminent researcher
和游戏方面的杰出研究专家
on speech recognition and gaming playing at Carnegie Mellon.
他既是恶魔又是上帝
He was a demon and god.
我有幸和他谈了几次
I got a chance to talk to him a few times,
当我把他的系统应用于卡内基梅隆大学的
when I adopted his system to one of the very first
第一个语音可控设备之后
speech controllable device in Carnegie Mellon.
最重要的是
And most of all,
我见识到了李开复博士
over the years I have learnt
这么多年来卓越的洞察力
Dr. Kai-fu Lee has an insight.
他的内心
He is, in his heart,
像一个16岁的孩子一样充满热情
as yound as a 16-year old, and as enthusiasm,
又像一位500岁的老人一样睿智
but as wise as a 500-year old.
欢迎开复
Welcome Kai-fu.
谢谢 谢谢塞巴斯蒂安
Thank you. Thank you Sebastian.
你太客气了
You are too kind.
我可是塞巴斯蒂安的忠实粉丝
I'm a huge fan of Sebastian,
因为他参与开发了谷歌、谷歌地图
for the work he has done at Google or for the maps
谷歌自驾车、谷歌 X实验室和优达学城
as well as for the self-driving car and Google X and Udacity
以及人们口耳相传的一些新事物
and some new things people rumor about.
嘘…..
shhhhhhhh.
我对他做的每件事情都有所关注
I follow up every thing he does.
别说啦
don't talk of that.
好的 秘密 秘密
OK. Secret, secret.
我是这里的主持人
I am here the moderator.
今天的主角是李开复
Today is all about Kai-fu Lee.
我们每个月都会开展一期
This is a series of Udacity Talks
优达学城专访
which we do every month or so,
我们会邀请如李开复等知名人士
where we bring luminaries like Kai-fu Lee to everybody,
来与大家（大部分是我们的学生）交流
most our students and among our students
我选取了我们学生提出的一些问题
I picked up some questions
与李开复互动
to interact with Kai-fu Lee.
但在此之前 我想问您几个问题
But before that I want to ask you a few questions.
我想回归本源
So I want to go back to the basics,
因为在我看来 人们通常将您视为
because I think people will view as an amazing investor
一名出色的投资者和商业领袖
and an amazing business leader in China.
但是他们并不太了解您是怎么起家的
But they don't really know what you start out with.
您曾经是一名黑客对吗?
You were a hacker right?
对 是的
yes, I was.
其实我曾经研究过你的代码
actually I worked on your code.
哦？
oho!
那个程序叫做“比尔”
and the program was called Bill
它是游戏奥赛罗
it was Othello game.
1984年
In 1984,
我是卡内基梅隆大学的二年级研究生
I was a second-year graduate student at Carnegie Mellon.
我教一群高中生编程
I taught a bunch of high school students how to program.
其中一个学生真的很聪明
One of the students was really smart.
他叫 Sanjoy Mahajan
His name is Sanjoy Mahajan.
后来 我和他一起开发了
And then I worked with him to
一个奥赛罗游戏程序
build an Othellogame program.
然后我们说 我们可以把它
And then we said well we could make it
变得像世界冠军一样棒
as good as world champion.
所以我们接着一起研究
So we went ahead and he and I worked together.
在卡内基梅隆大学 我们没有资金
At Carnegie Mellon we had no funding
只是为了好玩
just for fun developed this program
这个程序很快就被开发出来了
that was very fast
成了世界冠军比尔
and did the world champion called Bill.
为什么叫比尔呢？
why it was called Bill?
因为《奥赛罗》是一个
I called it Bill because Othello is a play
莎士比亚戏剧
written by Shakespeare
莎士比亚的姓是威廉
and Shakespeare's first name is William
而比尔是威廉的简称
and Bill is the short for William.
这段不可思议的历史值得为世人所知
this is an untold history but the world should know.
我们谈过谷歌阿尔法围棋
We talked about Google Alpha Go
它去年打败了世界围棋冠军
beating the world champion in Go last year.
大约在20年前
In 1997, about 20 years ago,
卡内基梅隆大学的后代"深蓝"
Deep Blue, an offspring of Carnegie Mellon,
战胜了 Gary Kasparov
beat Gary Kasparov
当时的国际象棋世界冠军
who was then considered the world champion in chess,
尽管存在一些争议
though there were debates about it.
但在此之前
But before that, Samuel the checkers game,
塞缪尔的西洋跳棋程序击败了一名
there was a great success in Carnegie Mellon that was
真正的跳棋大师
a strong authentic player was beaten by a virtual program.
那是您的杰作吗？
Is that yours?
那是一个微型程序
that was a micro program.
所以在 AI 游戏的历史上
so you were a reigning champion
您一度是个卫冕冠军
in the history of AI games
这是另一个非常受欢迎的游戏
well it was another very popular game.
我的确因为它在人工智能方面
I did get a publication
获得了一些知名度
in Artificial Intelligence.
太棒了
that was great.
看你的代码
I looked at your code
就能领略你精彩的编程方式
and I can tell the way you encoded was just brilliant.
这是一个生成你自己的代码的程序
It was a program to generate your own code.
一段能生成代码的代码
It was a code generating code.
这是一个预编程
it's a pre-programing.
基本上在计算机科学方面
Basically in computer science,
人们希望最大限度地减少繁琐的计算量
you want to minimize a massive amount of computing
因而创建了可以查找的表格
so you create tables that you could look up
并快速处理事务
and rapidly do things fast.
据我了解
As I understand it,
CMU 开发了一个新的德州扑克智能系统
CMU has a new Texas Hold'em poker player,
我认为这也有着巨大的潜力
I think they also generate a large space.
我觉得你30年前的开发
I think there are going to be footsteps
给了他们一些启发
that you started 30 years earlier.
他们学习了你的经验
That kind of learning.
是的
Yes.
然后你转到了一个叫 SPHINX 的程序
Then you moved on to something called SPHINX,
这可是世界上第一个真人发音
which was the world very first speaker voice
和语音识别系统
and speech recognition system.
你是怎么做到的？
How did that happen?
我去了卡内基梅隆大学
well I went to Carnegie Mellon
遇到了我们的系主任
and I met with our department chair,
尼克尔·哈博曼
Nichole Harborman.
尼克尔说十分欢迎开复
Nicole said Kai-fu welcome
我说您对我有什么期望吗？
and I said what do you expect from me?
他说我希望你在你所研究的领域创作一篇
He said I want you to write the best thesis
最棒的论文
in your area
我希望你无论做什么研究
and I want you to be the best in the world
都是世界上最棒的
in whatever thesis you do.
我说这真的很难
I said that is really hard
我不大可能是最棒的
and I cannot be the best.
他说你可以选择一个较窄的领域
He said you can pick a narrower area
你就能做到
and you will be the best.
语言识别这种狭窄的区域？
it doesn't matter a narrow area like speech recognition?
谁在乎呢?
who care
真是个糟糕的选择 呵呵
what a bad choice. hehehe
他说 "要在你的领域做出最好的研究成果
he just said, "write the best thesis in your area,
否则你就白来卡内基梅隆了"
otherwise this is not what Carnegie Mellon is about".
之后 我去和拉吉·瑞迪
Then I went to work with Raj Reddy on
一起研究语音识别
speech recognition.
拉吉建议我使用
Raj was suggesting that I should use Expert System
专家系统
for speech recognition.
嗯 我非常尊重拉吉
well, I respect Raj greatly.
那时候这个技术既流行
At that time, it was a very popular technology
又容易上手
and it is plausible.
一个叫 Victor Zhu 的人编写了一些新颖的程序
A guy named Victor Zhu writes special programs.
所以拉吉说 哎 我们来效仿 Victor Zhu 吧
So Raj said well let's just emulate the Victor Zhu.
所以我们干了一年
So I did that for one year
的确发表了一些成果
and we really published what we did
我发现我们走到了死胡同
and I saw it was an deadend
再走下去是没用的
and it wasn't going to work.
所以我不得不面对一个问题
So I had to face the issue,
我是否真的挑战了我的博士生导师
do I actually challenge my Ph.D advisor
尝试了不同的东西
and try something different
或者按照他所说的
or do what he says
研究了我的系主任说的不要做的事情
and graduate what my department chair said not to do.
所以我挣扎了一下 说
So I struggled a bit and said
"额 我真的想在这个领域里
"well, I really wanted to be the best thesis
有所成就
in this sub-category
但我不知道怎么改进"
but I didn't know how to make it better",
所以幸运的是 我遇到了彼得·布朗
so it was lucky that I met Peter Brown,
另一个在 IBM 学习的 CMU 学生
who was another CMU student studying at IBM,
他回来告诉了我隐马尔可夫模型
so he came back and told me the hidden Markov models
隐马尔可夫模型在当时
hidden Markov models at that time
可是一个神秘的新事物
had been a cryptic new thing.
是的 没人知道它
it was. No one knew about it.
它不是专家系统
It wasn't Expert System.
没有用于机器学习的代码规则
It has no rules of code in it for machine learning.
对
right.
令人惊奇的是 你有一台机器
It was fascinating that you had a machine
向它丢进一些数据 它会学习一些东西
that you could throw data and it learns what A and B and C.
它是现在深度学习的简洁版
It is kind of a simple version of deep learning today.
所以用了一个周末以后
So I implemented it over a weekend
我发现它太神奇了
and I saw that it was amazing.
我试过 Toy 数据
I tried to Toy Data.
那应该有用
I saw that should work.
我基本上会喝很多咖啡
I basically drank a lot of coffee
去找导师
and went to my advisor and said
说：“拉吉 我喜欢语音识别
"Raj, I love speech recognition
但我不会去用专家系统”
but I'm not gonna use Exper System"
他说 你想做什么
and he said what do you want to do.
我说我想用隐马尔可夫模型
I said I gonna use hidden Markov models
虽然那不一定有用
I am not sure that would work
我们争论了一会
and we debated for a while.
最后 他认识到我很固执
In the end, he saw that I was stubborn.
所以他说了一些话 这些话让我铭记终生
So he said something I remember my whole life.
他说 “开复 我不同意你的观点
He said, "Kaifu, Idon't agree with you,
但我支持你”
but I support you".
我认为这不仅是教授做过的
That I think was not the only most generous thing
最宽厚的事
a professor could do,
而且是一种令人赞叹的领导力
but also an amazing style of leadership.
如果你想领导聪明的人
If you want to lead smart people,
不要告诉他们要做什么
you cannot tell them what to do,
而要引导他们发挥自己的热情
you have to lead them to use their passion.
谢谢你
Thank you.
老实说 拉吉 如果你在看专访
Honestly, Raj if you were watching,
记得我们爱你
we love you.
你对卡内基梅隆的贡献
You work more for Carnegie Mellon
比任何人都多
than anybody else.
当我来到卡内基梅隆
I had been in the same theme
我一直研究同一个课题
when I came to the Carnegie Mellon
从来没有和你直接合作过
I had never worked with you directly,
和其他人合作
I worked with somebody else.
但我们俩的办公室是紧挨着的
But I was literally next door to your office.
彼得·布朗是一个有信誉影响力的人
Peter Brown is a person who had credit impact.
彼得很低调
Peter is very low profile.
不过你要是去谷歌搜他
But if you google him
你会发现他在 IBM 语音组工作
you will see that he worked in the IBM speech group.
他和鲍勃·默瑟做了第一个
He and Bob Mercer did the first
统计机器翻译项目
statistical machine translation.
神奇的是 那时候 每个人翻译的时候
It was fascinating at that time everybody
都死抠语法
translated by syntax,
导致翻译的版本差强人意
translated never quite what you want.
彼得和鲍勃说 我们用包模型
And Peter and Bob said is let's use the Bag Model,
让我们把单词全部整合到一起
let's take every word and do a mapping
来做两种语言里的单词的一一映射吧
of the word into another language.
我们再用另一种语言模型
Let's take another language model
把新的包放到一句话里
to put the new bags into one sentence.
语言学的东西是很玄乎的
The linguist thing is heretical;
你怎么可能做到这些呢？
how did you possibly do that?
这种做法把某物
This regards
当成了一种语言
Something like a language.
它们更有用
They work better.
所以他们用这个
So they used this.
我记得加拿大的国会辩论
I remember the Canadianparliamentary debates,
由于辩论内容直接从英文
because they were literally translated
翻译成了法文
literally from English to French.
需要一个巨大的语料库 对吧？
This is huge corpus of data, right?
是的 因为当时没有很多双语资料
Yes. Becauseat that time there was not much bilingual data.
加拿大国会一直都有能力
Canada was a country where the parliament
直接产出高质量的译文
has always a direct translation of very high quality one.
所以他们做到了这些
So they did that.
您是世界上第一位
you are one of the first machine learning people
机器学习者
in the world.
对
Yes.
他们就像你在卡内基梅隆研究语音识别一样
as you were at Carnegie Mellon for speech recognition
只是做了不同的语言翻译
but they did different language translation.
这是世界上第一台应用这个原理的机器
The first machine in the world to put the principle
接着它推动了谷歌和其他人打造了一流的
that then drove Google and others to build their amazing
语言翻译引擎
language translation engines.
没错 IBM 有很多天才
that's right. IBM has amazing people.
而作为一个旁观者
And, as a side note,
鲍勃·默瑟和彼得·布朗
Bob Mercer and Peter Brown
加入了 Resonance Technology
went off to join Resonance Technology,
它的对冲基金可能拥有
which was probably the highest return
世界上最高的回报定量
quantitative hedge fund in the world.
每年都有30-50％的回报
It's like 30-50% return every year.
是的 他们有两个基金
Yes. They have two funds.
他们自己的钱的基金的回报是 71%
For their own money they made 71%
全世界其他人的钱的基金回报是 30-50％
for the rest of the world they made 30-50%.
他们做得很好
They did very very well.
哈哈 我自己的投资只有5％的收益
I only make 5% in my daily trading activities.
然后你去了微软
Then you went to Microsoft
当我问你的时候 你提到的第一件事
and when I asked you about the very first thing
是你解雇了70名语言学家
you mention is you fired 70 linguists.
你声称你的名誉将毁于一旦
You claim you fame to fire.
关键不是我的名誉
it is not my fame.
其实那是个非常困难的时期
Actually it was a very difficult period.
因为我最初去微软
Because I went to Microsoft initially to
是建立微软中国研究院
found Microsoft Research China,
他们有大量的资金
which had huge amount of funds
雇了很多人去做有趣的事情
and hired a lot of people to do fun things.
总是件有趣的事 雇人
It is always fun to hire people
召集像您这样的人才
and bring people who are like you
赋予他们自由并与他们一起工作
and give them freedom and work with them.
那就是我们当时在微软中国研究院做的事
That was we did in Microsoft Research China.
这也是我们今天在创新工厂
That is what we do today
合资企业做的事
in Sinovation Ventures.
但是不幸的是 大概是因为我做得太好了
But unfortunately, I guess I did good enough jobs,
比尔·盖茨说 “开复很不错
said Bill Gates, "well Kai-fu is pretty good,
我们把他拉回来
let's pull him back to
给他一些有问题的团队
and let's give him some problematic teams
看看他会怎么做”
and see what he does."
给我的其中一支团队
And one of the teams he asked me to lead
是自然语言小组
was the natural language group,
叫 NLG 这个团队一共大概有 110 人
known as NLG. It was a team for about 110 people.
我猜都是博士 对吧？
PhD I guess, right?
110 个人基本上全是博士
110, mostly PhD.
其中70％是语言学家
70% of them are linguists,
但不一定是计算语言学家
not necessarily computational linguists,
也不一定懂计算
some are computational, some are not,
基本上他们没有写过任何代码
but basically they didn't write any code
也不懂算法
they didn't understand algorithms.
但是他们确实
But they did work very hard to
非常努力地完善每个英文句子
make every English sentence parcel as well as possible
还写了一些检测语法错误的规则
and they wrote rules to detect grammar errors.
所以出来的产品不算差
So the product isn't bad.
如果你用 Microsoft Word
If you use Microsoft Words,
语法检查功能也还行
the grammar checker isn't bad.
他们修复了相当多的错误
They fix a fair amount of errors.
但比尔说“开复 带着这110个人
But Bill says "Kai-fu, take these 110 people
去研究自然语言对话技术吧”
and turn them into a natural language dialog technology".
我跟团队谈了谈
I talked to the team
了解了这个技术
and I looked to the technology
然后说我没办法做这个
and I said there was no way
因为更多的语言学家不能解决问题
because the future cannot possibly be more linguistics
需要更多的统计学家
and there should be more statistics.
更准确地说
Just to put it correctly.
你曾经带领过70位世界级的语言学家
You took 70 world class linguists
而他们供职于最受推崇的微软公司
who were hired by the most revered company - Microsoft.
是的
Yes.
你觉得在这个小统计公式里
And you felt the little statistic formula,
其中有抽象的模式和数据
there was abstruct patterns and data
源于70名顶尖的专家 是吗？
that would be the 70 super smart experts. Yes?
是的
Yes, I did.
他们没有重新研究语法检查
They didn't re-implement the grammar checker
而是投入到了其他任何任务上
but on any other tasks yes they did.
所以回到数据上来说
so machine learning, back to the data,
你第一个捕捉到了机器学习
you were one of the very first striking eyes to witness
能击败人类专家的地方
where she beats human experts.
是的 不过当然
Yes, but of course
微软有很多人非常擅长机器学习
Microsoft has a lot of people who are very good
比如
in machine learning like.
我不是唯一的那个
I wasn't alone.
但不幸的是
But the group I inherited
我接手的那个团队第一步走错了
unfortunately had a wrong first step.
要想解雇70个人是很难的
It was very difficult to fire 70 people
这会对他们的家人产生极大的影响
and that had an impact to their family
他们不理解我的决定
and they didn't understand my decision
我们争论了很多次
and we had a lot of fighting
他们还向比尔抱怨
and they complained to Bill.
还好我们终于完成了项目构建
But we ended up the building,
如果你用 Windows Support
if you use the Windows Support today,
你可以手动输入你的问题
you type a question to say you have a problem
而如何修复这个问题
and how to fix something that was based
最终是基于我构建的系统
eventually on the system I built.
它的确很有用也很稳健
And it works. It is robust.
这是个智能系统
It is a very smart system.
不可能在语言系统的
It couldn't have been possible
框架下构建起来
to have been built under linguist system.
的确令人佩服
it's quite amazing,
因为你是我所在领域的杰出科学家之一
because you are one of the eminent scientists in my field.
人们专程来卡内基梅隆只为了和你握手
People come to Carnegie Mellon to shake your hand.
不 没那回事
No, not at all.
之后 您当了经理
and then you became a manager
做统计相关业务
and you did statistic business,
这个转变还比较大
which is a quite shift of career.
您后来去了一个搜索引擎公司
And then you moved to a search engine company,
不过名字我忘了
whose name I forgot.
哈哈哈
Hahaha.
能再告诉我们叫什么名字吗？
what's the name again
谷歌
Google.
呵呵 我应该听说过他们
Hehe. I should know them.
额 在中国它还不太普及
Well, it's not that known in China.
我猜你后来开始为谷歌在中国的发展
then you started your role in Google
做贡献 对吧？
in China I guess, right?
对 在2005年 我创立了谷歌中国
yes, I started Google China. 2005.
他们怎么看待
what have they said about between
谷歌中国和中国政府之间的关系？
Google China and China's government?
好像并不总是...
It wasn't always as…
嗯 谷歌总是很难
well, it was always difficult for Google
深入了解中国文化
to understand the Chinese culture.
这需要大量的实践
And this requires practice.
有什么区别？
what are the differences.
额
Well,
我会注意的
I will be carefully here.
嗯 有什么区别
Well, what are the differences.
我爱中国
I love China.
好的 我可以回答
Ok I can answer that.
你在谷歌工作过
You worked at Google.
我们都知道 谷歌的根本任务
We all know Google's fundamental mission
是整合世界各地的信息
is to organize the world's information
并随时提供给大家
and make it available to everybody at anytime.
所以我认为他们不能做到
So I think they take a special exception
这一点的情况是很少的
to situations where they cannot do that.
是的 关于中国法律和的辩论
Yes. Debates about Chinese laws and or on.
我赞同你
I agree with you.
那么继续.
Then press forward now,
你自己有一些资金
you have your own fund,
一组公司
a mount of money, you have a portfolio of companies,
个人孵化中心
your incubation center
是你令高效的人工智能
and you make efficient artificial intelligence
成为迄今为止最轰动的事
the biggest thing ever,
但你同时也会投资 我知道
but you also fund, I know,
我们已经展示了
we already showed girls
一些事业有成的女孩
who have aspiring career.
发生了什么？
What's happening?
嗯
well,
我在2009年创立了创新工厂合资公司
I founded Sinovation Ventures in 2009.
这不是"罪恶的欢呼" 而是"标志的欢呼"
it is not "sin ovation" but "sign ovation"
嗯 我称之为"标志的欢呼"
well I call it "sign ovation",
因为我们没犯罪
because we don't sin.
呵呵
hehe
我们没什么罪 我们尽量不这样
Well, we don't sin very much. We try not to.
我以为这是"罪恶的欢呼"呢
I thought it was "sin ovation".
也许是因为发音很像？
easy to pronounce, perhaps?
但 Sino 是中国的意思
But Sino is like China.
对 我知道
It is good. I know.
当我们创办创新工厂合资公司时
when we started the Sinovation Ventures,
我们想做所有的技术投资
we wanted to do all tech investing.
但当时大部分中国技术是模仿国外的
But at that time, much of tech in China were still copycats.
在这个阶段 人们想投资
It wasn't at a stage where you could really find to fund
一个AI公司、科技公司、数据库公司
an AI company or a tech company or a database company
或其他公司是很难的
or something.
因为市场规模大
Because the market is large
产品需求量大
and the need for product is large
但创造力
but the degree of creativity
和知识深度不够
and the depth of knowledge wasn't there.
所以我们不得不说 好吧
So we had to say, ok,
我们拿了投资者的钱就得赚钱
we took investors money we got to make money
所以我们要投资任何能赚钱的地方
so we gonna invest whatever makes money.
我们擅长
What we are good at is
技术方面
things that are propelled by technology.
所以我们把钱用在了
So we would invest in anything that fits
手机、AI和任何其他热点上
the exponential wave of mobile, AI, any other wave.
所以我们投资了一些不寻常的公司
So we invested in some very unusual companies
比如 SNH48
like the SNH48.
所以你用美金还是人民币投资？
so you take American money or take Chinese money?
我们两个都用
we take both.
SNH48 不算一个真正意义上的技术公司吧
SNH48 is not an exact tech company.
你知道他们有一些技术
There is some tech, you know
这是个众包的大数据公司
It's a crowd sourcing, big data company.
别不好意思 这公司很棒
Don't be ashamed, it is great.
是的 我真的很惊讶
Yes. I was really surprised
塞巴斯蒂安竟然知道他们
Sebastian knew about them.
我不知道你们当中谁知道 SNH48
I don't know few of your guys know SNH48.
这已经是一种投资了
That is already an investment.
我们是第一批投资者
We are the first investors.
因为我们看到 观看这些电视节目
Because we saw that watching these shows on TV
只会产生大量的收入
was only going to generate so much revenue,
如果你能让人们参与投票和花钱
if you could have people participate and vote and pay.
这是个更大的机遇
That is much bigger opportunity.
那就是我们的理念
That was the concept we have.
我们都看电视
we all watch TV and
和游戏节目
their game shows,
美国的人才都聚集在了一起
American talents, come together in one world.
我有个问题
Here is a question I wondered about.
当我还是孩子的时候
When I was a kid.
我隐约感觉日本会统治世界
I was kind of known that Japan would rule the world,
日本会成为动态随机存取记忆体
like, Japan became the epicenter for DRAM
半导体行业和超强性能 CPU 的技术中心
and for most semi-conductor and very exceptional CPUs.
日本的投资不可磨灭
And Japan made an investment which cannot disappear.
而过去十年
And the last ten years,
我们知道中国引领了世界
we have known the China has taken off the world.
而且和日本有区别
And there is a difference.
日本与中国的
What's the difference in the
成功秘诀有什么区别？
recipe between Japan and China?
呵呵 我不太了解日本
Well I'm not an expert in Japan.
但是我的一个朋友最近
But one of my friends recently
接手了一家日本公司
took over a Japanese company
他描述了他看到的一些日本人的优缺点
and he described the good and bad things he saw.
优点是注意细节
The good things are attention to detail.
他们注重极小的技术问题
Extreme value of tiny technical issues
努力确保事情完美无缺
and making sure things are done flawlessly and beautifully.
缺点在于日本文化不是比较饥饿的文化
The problem is that it is not a very hungry culture.
人们不对抗 只是努力工作
People don't fight and work extremely hard.
他们的努力程度不及中国人
They work hard but not as hard as in China.
而且 他们比较注重阶级
And also, it is very hierarchical.
我朋友称 你知道董事会
So he described in a board meeting,
有四个级别
you know there are four layers of tables,
当有问题要讨论的时候
and when issues came up for discussion,
高级副总裁会转向副总裁
the senior VP would turn around to their VPs
问他们答案
and say what is the answer to that.
副总裁转向董事
The VP would turn around to the directors,
董事转向经理
and director to the managers,
经理转向普通员工
manager would turn around to the individual contributor
然后他们会叫某人去做事和传播信息
then they would call somebody and information propagates up.
这就像一个我听过的游戏
it is like a hear game
你们一直重复这个词
where you repeat the word
直到最后你会问这是原来那个词吗？
and you gonna say this is the same word?
是的 我认为中国的大公司
yes. I think large companies in China
建立了等级文化
build a hierarchical culture
管理层并没有创造自己的价值
where management didn't add their value.
等等 你们中国有很多大公司
but, hold out, you have large companies,
有阿里巴巴、腾讯、百度、京东
you have Alibaba, Tencent, Baidu, JD.
这些公司怎么避免这种情况？
How do these companies avoid it?
以阿里巴巴为例
I will take Alibaba as an example.
我认为马云的聪明之处
I think Jack Ma is a brilliant,
在于他重塑公司的方式
in the way he reinvents the company.
任何不断壮大的公司都会遇到一个问题
Any company that gets big would have a problem of
聪明人感觉自己的能力达到了上限
smart people feeling like reach their ceiling,
好像没有进步空间了
like cannot go up anymore.
所以马云把他的公司分成……
So Jack organizes his company in,
我不太记得具体数字….. 25个团体
I don't how many, 25 groups,
每个团体都是一个独立的公司
each of which is an independent company
每个公司都有一个顶峰
with a pinnacle that is a truly
是其所在区域真正的十亿美元的公司
billion-dollar company in its zone
有负责管理经理的CEO
with CEO taking responsibility accountable for the managers
马云让经理轮岗
and he rotates them
每个人都觉得他自己是CEO
but each person feels like they are a CEO.
他们觉得 就好像 如果你是财务总监
They feel like, it is like, if you are a financial CEO,
你不会想离开去另一家公司
you don't want to leave and do to another company,
因为你本来就管理着一个大公司
because you are running as big a company as you can imagine.
然而 所有25家公司都有一致的文化
Yet, all the 25 companies have a consistent culture.
所以他也能引领和
So he is also able to lead
复制一点阿里巴巴的发展策略
and replicate a little bit Alibabas.
这使他们相对灵活
That keeps them relatively nimble,
专注 遵循一贯的文化
focused yet consistent culture.
我认为也许
That kind of,
Alpabet 是这种模式下的一个尝试
I think maybe Alpabet is an attempt to this.
Alpabet和伯克希尔·哈撒韦公司
Alfabet and Berkshire Hathaway
有相同之处
have a same flavor of it.
是的 所以我认为我们需要创新企业模式
yes. So I think we need to innovate in corporate model,
阿里巴巴、Alpabet
Alibaba, Alpabet,
伯克希尔·哈撒韦就是这样做的
Berkshire Hathaway are ones that have.
我想也许日本大公司
I think maybe the Japanese companies
还做不到这个
when are large cannot do that.
人工智能真是太有趣了
interesting interesting. Artificial intelligence.
当然
Yes.
你曾经在卡内基梅隆讲的一个话题
a topic that you started at Carnegie Mellon.
正好也是我当时谈论的话题
I was also being around and in the same topic.
你当时正全身心地投入工作
You have dedicated whole of your energy to it.
工作于该地区的一家内部创业公司
You worked in a in-house start-up company in the area.
能说说它为什么对你这么重要么
Tell about it. Why is important.
嗯 我觉得AI很重要
well, I think AI is important.
因为它能改变一切
Because it will change everything.
它比手机要重要得多
It is much more important than mobile.
手机是一个新设备
Mobile is a new devise.
也的确很重要
It's very important.
这是一种能将我们
It's a new device
大多数人联系在一起的新设备
that connects most of us.
但AI不仅仅关乎人类 还影响着商业
But AI is not just to people, but to business.
它将重塑商业 令它从传统转向
It is going to reinvent businesses from traditional
娱乐和互联网
to entertainment to internet.
每个公司 每一件事都会因此受到影响
Every company, every thing, is impacted.
塞巴斯蒂安比任何人
Sebastian, more than any body,
都了解自动车辆
knows about autonomous vehicles.
它将会改变交通
That is going to change the future of
运输的未来
transportation and delivery.
想想财务、一切与金融相关的
You think about finance, everything financial,
银行、保险、交易、证券、投资
banking, insurance, trading, security, investment.
他们都有硬伤
They are all built wrong.
做这些工作的人并不擅长这些
The people doing these jobs are not good at it,
因为总有一些磕磕绊绊
because there are a number of crunching jobs.
人永远不可能和机器一样
People can never be machines.
所以大多数这些人会被机器所取代
So most of these people would be replaced by machines,
机器不仅更聪明 更准确
who are not only smarter, more accurate,
也不会累 不会情绪化
but also they don't get tired, they are not emotional.
机器将在全世界大大提升效率
This will create a huge amount of efficiency in the world.
这就是我们要研究它的原因
That's why we work on it
因为它具有巨大的经济价值
because it has so much economic value,
而且我还可以解释其AI
but also because another role I can play
对中国的潜在影响
is to explain its potential impact of AI in China
因为它会冲击所有领域
because this will disrupt all the areas.
你知道的
You know.
我们已经在教育系统
The education system we have it wrong.
银行系统上犯了错
The banking system is wrong.
考虑到AI的冲击
And all these things, because of the AI disruption,
我们需要为下一代做好准备
we need to prepare our next generations to be ready,
因为如果他们接受的教育
because if they are being educated
使得他们做重复性的工作
to become skilled in some repetitive work,
就会被AI取而代之
it would be replaced by AI.
他们需要考虑如何
They need to look at how to
规划自己的职业和教育
plan their careers and education before that.
另一个问题 我和你的角度一样
another question, which I have the same position as yours.
但是我想听听你的回答
But I want to hear your answer.
我们中间有75％的人在办公室做
75% of us work in office jobs,
基本上是重复的工作
in basically repetitive jobs.
所以你刚才告诉我
So you just told me
每个人都会被电脑所取代
that each of them will be replaced by computer.
当然
of course.
这些人会怎么样？
what gonna happen to these people?
好的 有几种可能的猜测
well, there are several possible speculations.
我猜优达学城没有
I guess it comes out that Udacity hits
培养这类人（稍微）
none of these (sort of).
那是 如果你第一次这样做
that yes. If you first do that.
再教育 的确是这样
Reeducation, yes.
首先 不要太恐慌
Well, first of all. Not to panic too much.
因为这些强大的AI机器
Because there will be taxes generated
会产生税收
by these amazing AI machines
税收会给人们带来收益
and taxed will feed the people.
所以民主是社会主义的
so democracy would be socialist.
我的意思是企业所得税可能是70％
I mean corporate gains tax might be like 70%,
而不是30％
not 30%.
你我都必须缴纳很多税
you and I have to pay a lot of taxes.
但没有人会饿
But no one would go hungry.
这就解决了一个大问题
So that solves the big problem.
但那些被替代的人做什么呢
But what do they do.
我认为他们应该想想一些
I think one is they think about
需要深刻创意才能的工作
do they have deep creative talent.
显然 有的人得到了一个机器人程序后
Obviously, someone got a program to robots
成为了下一个毕加索
and becomes the next Picasso.
第二 他们能否做AI不能做的事情
Secondly, can they take on something that AI cannot do.
还有很多事情 AI做不了
There are still a lot of things that AI cannot do.
你明白的 艺术、电影、幽默
You know. Art, movies, humor,
手工艺、园艺
crafts, gardening.
所有这些事情
All those things.
都需要大量劳力
There are plenty of jobs that remain there.
服务业的劳力需求最大
The largest quantity will be in services,
例如 打扫、做饭
such as, you know cleaning, kitchen,
照顾孩子和老人
taking care of the kids, taking care of elderly.
而我认为今天的服务工作在社会上
And I think service jobs today don't get enough
没有得到足够的重视和尊重
attention and respect in the society
我们必须做出改变
and I think we have to change that.
我认为日本其实是一个非常好的例子
I think Japan actually is a very positive example of that.
如果你去日本
If you go to Japan,
会看到那些努力做饭或切寿司的人
people who work so hard to make a bowl or to cut sushi,
受到了神一样的待遇
they are treated like gods.
但现在有些公司基本上
but there are now companies that basically
都有做食物的机器人
have robots that make your food,
叫做加利福尼亚的
that is called in California
你可能见过
which you might know that
在手机上订购食物
you order your food in your phone
进入商店时食物已经准备好了
and when you enter the store, that is already ready
准备食物的可能是机器人
and robots can prepare food for you.
但是我们必须相信
but we have to believe.
我是个美食家
I'm a foodie,
我坚信人类会做出更好的食物
so. I firmly believe that humans will make better food
如果你用心了
and if you put in your love,
所有的日本寿司厨师用心了
that all Japanese sushi chefs put in,
我觉得食物会变得更好吃
I think the food would taste better
因为人们有更多的技能...
because there are more skills…
来吧 像你说的
come on, there is a data-crunching job,
这里有一个数据压缩的工作
in your own words.
有台机器可以制作一千块寿司
Like, a machine can make a thousand pieces of Sushi.
这不仅仅是切块 对吧？
well it is not just about cutting, right?
它包括准备、选材
It includes preparing, choosing.
我想浪漫一点
I'd like to be romantic a little bit
认为还应该有服务行业
and think there are service jobs.
你才是对的 我错了
And I even you are right and I'm wrong.
呵呵
hehe
虽然服务行业一直不受人们尊重
but even if service jobs cannot be revered,
但是我们仍要努力
we have to try,
毕竟大多数人将来从事的还是服务业
because most of the population will be service jobs.
如果我们能够尊重这些人的话
If we treat these people with respect,
还会觉得这些工作是不合需要？
if we feel these jobs are undesirable,
还会把服务人员视为二等公民吗？
if we treat service people as second class citizens,
不会
it won't.
当然
I agree.
不管怎么说
whenever we can,
为了使服务行业得到更多人的尊重
to make service jobs more respectable,
是时候发明一些新的东西了
maybe we have to invent some.
比尔?盖茨在他最近的文章中
Bill gates, in his recent article,
谈到了同情心  是这样吗？
talked about compassion. Right?
也许机器人可以替代人类来照顾
Maybe the people displaced by robots can take care of
流离失所的老人、残疾人
the elderly, take care of the handicapped,
托儿所的孩子
one-on-one nursery homes.
也许这些工作不能快速产生经济价值？
And these are not jobs generating immediate economic value?
但是 他们酝酿出的是爱
But they generate love and they
并帮助创建人与人之间的联系
create human to human connection.
这是一个伟大的愿景
that is a great great vision.
开复 我很喜欢跟你聊天
So, Kai-fu, I love talking to you.
天哪！ 我真的学到了很多
My god. I learned so much.
我知道的就是大概有
One of the things I will do is on behave of
七十万学生
probably seven hundred thousand students
正在收看直播
watching on-line right now,
谁来给我们提问
who sent us questions,
在节目开始之前
I guess I have piece of paper
我准备了一张纸
that I got just before the show
我想要把学生的问题带给你
and I love ask the students' questions to you,
因为对优达学城的学生来说
because you have such a great situation
这是一个非常重要的时刻
to Udacity's students at this point.
有一个叫Josie的学生
There is a person who called Josie
她的问题是关于人工智能（AI）的
and she is asking about AI,
她想要问你在当今社会
and she asks in your opinion, what is the most mature
AI技术中最成熟的应用是什么？
application of AI technology in the industry today?
今天？
today?
最成熟的要数搜索引擎了
Well the most mature that would have to be search engines.
因为我们每天都在用它
Because we use it everyday.
在搜索引擎后面
Behind the search engine,
不仅有匹配字段来帮助获取词语
not only there is a matching words to get words,
在点击后就会出现你想要了解的东西
but there is a learning what things people click on.
它有一定的知识层级
It has a hierarchy of knowledge,
就像当你去谷歌 去百度时
like when you go to Google, go to Baidu,
我要用你的名字作为例子
and I will use your name as an example,
如果你去谷歌搜索谁是 巴斯蒂安?特伦
if you go to Google to search who is Sebastian Thrun,
就会出来有关你的介绍
your biography comes out
因为它有一个和你的信息
because it has a knowledge representation,
相匹配的知识表示
it has a matching,
当你点击该结果时
and when you click on that result,
就会加强搜索并得到更多的正确答案
it will get reinforced and get more answers correctly.
在我看来 搜索引擎已经存在了
So I think search engine
很长时间 并且经证实
has been around for a long time and proven,
我觉得这是最成熟的例子了
I think that's certainly the most mature example.
正如你所言
as you are visionary,
实际上在这样一个亚马逊和新设备及移动设施
how will search engines look ten years from now
引领潮流的时代 搜索引擎将如何应对
in the age of Amazon Echo and new devices
接下来的这十年？
and mobile, actually.
实际上搜索引擎算不上最成熟的技术
well, search engines actually are not very smart,
你有没有想过？
do you think about it?
你问一个问题
You ask one question;
它会给出十种答案
it gives you you know ten mission answers.
通常你会看到一个页面有十条搜索结果
Usually you look at ten in one page,
即使你忽略第一页
even you ignore the first page,
还是会给你十种答案
give you ten answers,
这是一个非常棘手的问题
it's a very tricky interface.
因为我们不知道正确答案是在哪个页面上
Because we, when the right answer is on that page
而对于这些你本不了解的东西
and something you don't know
你是否该会感到开心呢？
if you are happy,
即使是弹出答案了 也许只有50-60％的
even through the pop-up answers only right
可能性是你想要的
maybe 50-60% at the time.
所以我想十年后
So I think ten years from now,
我想要搜索引擎能够理解你的问题
I like the search engine to understand what you say
并给出正确答案
and give you the answer,
而这个答案正好是你要找的
one answer that you are looking for.
所以你正在建立一个"聊天插件"
so you are building a "chat bar" right now,
你想要在新的搜索引擎上
is that you want to be detective
进行探测吗？
in terms of new search engine?
你指的是哪个系统？
what system?
你正在Sinovations建立
so you are building a "chat bar" right now here,
一个"聊天插件"
in Sinovations,
因此你是想...
that you want to be…
呵呵 聊天插件？
hehe, Chat Bar.
起来像是一种搜索引擎 还是...
is it like a search engine or…
我们说过谈话不会涉及到绝密内容
we said we won't talk about your secret project,
所以还是来谈谈其他吧
so we should talk about my secret project either.
抱歉 我晓得了
sorry.I got it.
下一个问题来自Ted
The next question is from Ted.
我们都觉得AI技术是非常强大的
We all agree that AI is very powerful already.
但Ted抱怨说
But Ted complains, he says at present,
语音识别软件不能完全准确地
I cannot fully depend on voice recognition software to
检测到他所说的话 尤其是中文
accurately detect what I'm saying, especially, in Chinese,
最好是普通话  这是为什么？
it should be mandarin. Why is that?
是这样的 语音识别系统
well, the speech recognition system
最近已经有所改善
has been improved a lot lately.
如果你使用的是kedaxunfei的
So if you use the newest version from
最新版本  ifly科技或百度
kedaxunfei, ifly tech, or baidu,
它的准确性应该是相当高的
the accuracy should be quite high.
一个原因可能是由于你的口音
One possible reason is your accent.
但我觉得当今大多数中国人的口音
But I kind of doubt it because most Chinese people's accent
还是可以的
is pretty moderate today.
这个叫Ted的
the name is Ted.
可能是一个正在学习中文的美国人
He might be an American who is learning Chinese.
这样啊 那么请不要讲外语
well, then. Don't speak foreign language.
可能的话 我会给你们两个解释
It could be. I'll answer twice.
如果作为一个中国人
If you are Chinese,
在语音识别时遇到问题
who has trouble with Chinese speech recognition,
我觉得可能是你故意这样说的
my answer is you'd probably talk deliberately.
语音识别系统的是
The way the speech recognition system works,
针对自然语言的培训
is that they are trained on natural speech,
所以你应该这么说
so you should talk like this.
相反地 你知道
If instead, you know,
如果当你和一个小宝宝说话的时候
when you talk to a little baby, right,
你说喝牛奶
you say drink your milk,
他会说什么？
he will say what?
喝！你！牛奶！
Drink, Your, Milk!
如果你这样做的话 语音识别就会扰乱
If you do that, the speech recognition will get confused,
声音太大 就会造成麻烦
you are too loud, you cause trouble.
所以不要故意这样说话
So don't talk deliberately.
也不要抠字眼
Don't try to talk like, try to emphasize words.
语速就保持你跟其他人
Just talk like you talk to another person
说话那样
at the same pace and speed.
可能这就是原因吧
That's probably the likely reason.
而且 当你切换输入法（IME）
And also, when try to dictate to a IME,
或敲打键盘时
or the keyboard,
它一开始也不是英文的
it doesn't do English
而且不可能一下子就出现你要输入的词语
and it doesn't do proper names very well.
所以你要非常小心
So you got to be careful.
你懂得  "我想要写一封信"
You know. "I'd like a letter to",
并且输入"李开复" 是这样吗？
and stop and type in "Kai-fu Lee". Right?
因为它的字典中没有李开复
Because it doesn't have Kai-fu Lee in its dictionary.
所以 当你敲打的词语是不常见的或英语时
So when you do proper names that are unusual or English,
为什么不说话呢？
don't you speech,
你可以停下来输入语音
you pause and type it in,
或者你将语音添加到它的词汇组里
or you teach it to add it to its vocabulary.
如果你和Ted一样是个外国人
If Ted, you are foreigner,
那么 你正好多了个中文老师
well, get a Chinese teacher
来帮助你提高中文水平
and improve your Chinese.
Sally是优达学城的一名学生 她来自美国
Sally is a Undacity student from the United States.
她问了一个非常有趣的问题
She asked a very interesting question,
我认为你是世界上唯一能够给出答案的人
I think you are the single in the world to answer,
那就是根据你在硅谷多年的经历
which is, you have been in Silicon Valley a lot,
你觉得硅谷的AI技术发展
what's in your opinion the difference between
与中国的AI技术发展
AI technology development in Silicon Valley
有什么区别呢？
and here in China?
好的 这是一个很好的问题
ok, it's a good question.
在我看来 在美国的这样一个大环境下
I think AI technology in Silicon Valley tends to be,
硅谷的AI技术更趋向于提出新算法
invent new algorithm, find new applications,
开拓新的应用领域
build within the American environment.
人们往往对企业有很多的想法
And people tend to think about enterprise a lot.
因为AI技术基本上
Because AI, fundamentally,
是服务于企业的应用程序
is an enterprise application,
而并非为消费者服务
not really a consumer app.
你不也在开发一个能促进银行、公司
You are selling a solution to make a bank, or a company,
或医院更好发展的解决方案吗？
or a hospital do something better.
因此我觉得美国企业家和AI企业家
So I think the American entrepreneurial AI entrepreneurs
更倾向于研究商业应用程序
tend to look at business applications
就像IBM的超级电脑"沃森"？
like IBM Watson
就像沃森努力发掘癌症或肿瘤的方法一样
like Watson style for trying to find cancer or tumors.
这可以说这既是个大问题又是个小问题
So they could be big problems or small ones,
但这正好符合企业数据仓库化
but the kind of fit within the data warehousing
建设的目标
enterprise direction.
在中国 这种问题到处都是
In China, they are all over the place.
反而我觉得在中国这种数据更容易获取
I think in China, the data is more accessible
导致中国的很多的需求
and the Chinese society has a lot of
得不到满足,
needs that are not fulfilled
因为过去200多年来逐美国社会
because the American society and economy which developed
和经济发展缓慢
gradually and slowly over the last 200 years or so.
好在过去35年里中国迅速发展
But the China society rapidly grew up in the last 35 years.
在这个过程中 还有很多差距尚未填补
In that process, there are many gaps that are unfilled,
因此我觉得中国企业家
so I think the Chinese entrepreneurs
更倾向于寻找这些差距
tend to look for those gaps
然后越过差距去解决问题
and jump in and try to solve the problems.
例如对智慧金融的投资
So one example is our investment in smart finance.
这家公司成立于在18个月前
That is company that was founded 18 months ago
这一年他们都在做小额贷款
and this year they are doing small loans.
只要下载一个应用程序
You have an app,
将你的数据上传至这个应用
you upload your data,
那么在八秒内就可以把钱转到手机上
and then you get your money to your phone in eight seconds.
而在美国你根本不需要这些东西
So that's something in the US you don't need
因为大家都有信用卡
because all of you have a credit card.
实际上是
actually it is because of a legal
美国的
(inaudible) in the United States,
银行业务亏损
who is a banking loss
各种simitations
various simitations,
自从2007年的金融危机以来
since 2007's financial crisis,
很难给你提供在线贷款
make it hard to give you an online loan.
的确是这样
is that right, ok, well.
其实中国是唯一
So, the Chinese opportunities
有这种待遇的国家
then in fact very uniquely Chinese,
所以这个公司在上个月放款150万元
so this company made 1.5 million loans in the last month.
太不可思议了
that's incredible.
你可以看到
so you can see that,
一旦在这种连续性的
when you have these gaps that are created
指数增长中途出现差距
by this continuity in the middle of exponential growth,
所有的中国企业家
all the Chinese entrepreneurs are there
都会抓住这样的机会
smelling for such opportunities.
我刚说什么来着？
what you just said blows my mind.
一个月一百五十万的贷款 简直太疯狂了
Look at the number of 1.5 million loans in a month is crazy.
中国的恐慌（？）
The thing of scare (???) of China,
这个数据的确
and yes the availability of data,
也许是由于中国的发展过程中
maybe it's regulatory opportunities
存在诸多不确定因素
in the course of uncertainties
监管单位已经学会抓住这些机会
that characterize China.
这使得万事皆有可能
That makes things possible.
我得想想
I have to think about it.
我想知道有没有哪条法律
I wonder if it's right to have a law that
规定不能在线借钱 有这回事吗？
doesn't permit borrowing money online, is that really …
在线借钱是可以的
borrowing money online is ok,
但是在美国 这样一个收取大额回报
but a bank putting you pressure and then
并使你感到压力山大的银行是不可能的
charging large returns is impossible in the United States.
信用额度有一定的限制
There is a regulation on the credit rates you can charge.
如果你遵守监管单位的信用额度
If you go to the regulatory credit rates,
企业可能不会
a business may not be,
因为企业每年可能会
because a business might charge
收取30％的费用
30% a year.
这可是一大笔收入
A large amount of returns.
智慧融资的独特之处就是AI技术
well, the unique thing about smart finance is the core AI
拥有较低的贷款不良率业
that does the loan has a very low bad loan rate.
实际上他们的利率也可以非常灵活的
So they actually can have flexible interest rates,
即使有上限
even there is ceiling.
不错呀
that's great.
John问了一个问题 与你创建的
John asked a question about your venture,
创新工场（Sinovation Ventures）有关
Sinovation Ventures.
他想知道在AI行业的所有领域中
He wants to know among all segments of AI industry,
你和Sinovation Ventures
which areas are you
最看好的是哪一个？
and Sinovation Ventures most interested in?
当你给AI创业者做投资时
What characters do you value,
你比较珍惜哪种人才？
when you invest in an AI entrepreneur?
哪些方面你比较关注？
What do you care about?
没错
Right, right.
我们比较看好金融领域
So, our interest area is in the financial area.
不仅包括贷款 还包括投资
That includes not only loans but also investments,
保险 银行等等
insurance, banking and so on.
所有有关金融的这些方面
All of them, all these financial aspects
都是人们发明的游戏 纯数字游戏
are games invented by people, pure numbers.
所以 正好适合AI
So, perfect for AI.
不需要本钱 也不需要动手 非常方便
No rose to rise, no hands to move, any of that.
只需要操作这些数字
So, they are purely frictionless numbers to put through.
这就是为什么我们对其感兴趣的原因
That's why we like that.
我们也做投资
We do investment as well,
包括两个无人驾驶汽车
but we also have two autonomous vehicle investments,
机器人
we have some robotic investments,
以及人脸识别投资项目
we have investment in face recognition,
我们的确投资了很多的其他项目
so we do invest in many other things,
但金融是我们最喜欢的
but financial is our favorite.
现在第二个问题是我们在寻找什么
Now the second part of the question is what do we look for.
我们绝对不会寻找更加智能的算法
We absolutely do not look for smarter algorithms,
因为今天的AI技术是所有已知的技术
because today AI is such that, all the known technologies,
（如深度学习）中做的比较好的
such as deep learning, are good enough
但是在应用领域仍然没有得到充分利用
and still not fully exploited in the application areas,
就像企业家 风投
as entrepreneurs, VCs,
明明现有的AI技术已经完全
it's irresponsible to have
能够解决问题了
invented new algorithms
但是他们还是不负责任地发明新的算法
to solve problems when existing ones are good enough.
我们鼓励大学的研究实验室能够做到这一点
We encourage university's research labs to do that.
因此 我们寻求的是那些能够对这种持续性
So we look for those entrepreneurs who have sharp eye
或机会拥有敏锐眼光的企业家
on this continuity or opportunity
以创造一个快速创造价值的公司
to create a company that rapidly creates value.
所以 这就是生意
so, business.
是生意 一种商业理念
business, business sense.
AI技术的出现是理所当然
take AI for granted,
要关心的是在生意中
and focus on business,
如何赚钱 赚谁的钱
how to make money, who gonna pay,
谁做决定 要赚多少钱...
who makes the decision, how much they gonna pay…
确实如此
exactly.
我们希望技术人员是
And then we want the technologist
一名非常务实的实践人员
to be a very practical practitioner
能够选择正确的算法然后再用于解决问题
that picks a right algorithm and puts it to work.
估计你怎么也不会想到我...
you will never find me…
Sebastian 我们可一直在关注着你呢！
we will always find you Sebastian.
我想要金融民主化
I want the democratization,
那怎么赚钱呢？
so how do you make money?
呵呵  好吧
Hehe. Ok.
Timmy和Carol问了一个综合性的问题
So, Timmy and Carol asked a combined question.
你曾经说过大约90％的重复性工作
Timmy is a person who mentioned that you once talked about
将被AI技术替代
some 90% of repetitive jobs will be taken over by AI.
你有这样说过？
You said that.
我曾经是说过
I said specifically once.
Timmy 想知道现在最有可能
they know want to know, Timmy wants to know which are
被取代的是哪一类工作
the most likely to be taken over now.
而 Carol 想知道对于长远来说
And carol wants to know which is the safest job
哪一类工作最安全
in the long term.
同样的问题
Kind of the same question,
作为一名本科生
which should I study as an undergraduate
我应该先提问哪一个才能不被你打乱
to have a chance not to be disrupted by Kai-fu.
好的 我们可以举个例子
well, we can give examples.
大家知道吗？
You know.
商人正在被替换
Traders are being replaced right now.
在华尔街 几乎没有生意可做了
In Wall Street there are hardly trades left,
全都是自动化的
that's all automated.
其次 我们重申一遍
Again, we reaffirm the point that
金融是最好的 AI 技术应用程序
finances are the best AI app.
而且你也知道 某些工作 尤其是
But also you know, certain jobs,
有特殊要求的工作 工人是危险的
particular character degree jobs,
这是因为工厂机器人的出现
because of factory robotics.
司机将面临危险 可能不会很快
Drivers will be in danger, probably not soon,
但是会有很大一部分人面临危险
but there are a large percentage of people.
而对于保安人员来说
And security guards,
用相机也可以达到同样的效果
because watching them with cameras would be almost as good
不要认为这是一对一的替换
And don't think this as a replacing one for one.
例如 如果你需要十名保安人员
For example if you have ten security guards,
守卫一个大工厂
guarding a big factory,
或许你还需要另外一个
maybe you still have one
那将是机器人相机
and the other nigh will be robotic cameras.
不仅仅是这类蓝领工作 .
And also don't think of this blue collar job only,
我觉得很多医生也会被替换
because I think many doctor jobs will get be replaced.
例如 我们不想成为放射科医生
For example, we wouldn't want to be a radiologist,
因为你要查看所有有关这些肿瘤
because you will read all these pictures for tumors and
或类似东西的放射片
things like that.
但是 机器操作起来就好多了
But this is much better done by machine.
还没有对它们输入足够的数据和进行培训
They just haven't got enough data and training yet.
但总有一天 它们会做到的
But someday, they will.
所以我觉得很多这些工作 一项项概括..
So I think a lot of these jobs, one generalization…
哪一类工作最安全了？
what's the safest job.
喜剧演员
safest job would be a comedian,
精神科医生 他们是最安全的
psychiatrist, that is pretty safe.
不 未必
no, no, no.
这可能是由于数据还没有达到一定的程度
it's maybe there are not enough data.
额 好吧
Ok.
任何能够夺人眼球
anything that that requires personal attention,
且对创造力有一定要求的东西
anything that requires creativity,
才是真正富有艺术创造力
true artistic creativity.
经验法则告诉你哪些事情
One rule of thumb is the job you do
可以做
can be done with something.
但不总是真的 只是大致如此
Not always true, but roughly.
问题是你提到全球AI技术方面
the question is you mentioned shortage of
人才欠缺
AI related talents globally.
为什么会有这样的问题以及如何解决呢？
Why there is such a shortage and how to solve it?
你有什么可以解决这个问题的办法吗？
Do you see any solution to this challenge?
好的 这可以为优达学城
ok. This gonna be an advertisement for
深度学习课程做一次广告
Udacity courses of deep learning.
我认为问题在于...
I think the shortage is…
学习AI技术需要扎实的
it does require good fundamentals
计算机科学和数学基础
in computer science and mathematics to learn AI
并不是每个人都可以做到这一点
and not every body has that.
它不只是从教科书中学习
And it is not learning only from the textbook.
还需要一个好老师
Doing, requires a good teacher,
能够一对一
who is on one-on-one.
所以 我认为这是非常好的
So, I think it is very good,
并不是每个大学
and I think not every university
都要进行这样的教学
should be in place to teach that.
在线教学是让你进入状态并且操作自如的
So online teaching as the first step to get you in,
关键一步
and feel comfortable,
如果你想取得进步 那么你可以尝试下一步
if you want to make progress then you can try to the next,
找一个导师 找一份工作 学习...
getting a mentor, getting a job, learning…
这是我的团队
This is my team,
这里我要做一些说明 此处应该加上括号
put here my notes and say, in brackets,
"Sebastian
"Sebastian,
你可以介绍一下 Udacity 是做什么的"
you could introduce what is Udacity doing here",
我要以一个很短的商业广告
and I should start a short commercial
作为开始
预计该广告今天就能推出
the commercial is expected to be launched today,
这是我们深度学习课程的中文版
a Chinese version of our deep learning curriculum,
也是最受欢迎的课程
the most popular curriculum.
这是世界上唯一的深度学习课程
It's the only deep learning curriculum in the world.
目前还没有中文版本
There are no versions of Chinese right now.
它主要由Google完成
and it's done by Google mostly
然后进行出版
and published a most popular deep learning.
深刻学习课程非常受欢迎
Deep learning is here with a crazy demand.
如果你是一名滴滴司机
So you are a DD driver
但是你不喜欢你的工作
and you don't like your job.
（当然我喜欢滴滴 ）
I love DD.
你想要增加薪水
And you want to double your salary,
深度学习就可以帮你实现这一点
deep learning is exactly the magic that the people do
而你所谈论的大部分有关AI技术
and most of the AI exactly
其实就是深度学习
you talk about is about deep learning.
所以有一个中文版的Udacity.com
So there is a Chinese version of Udacity.com.
如果您在接下来的两天内注册
In the next two days we will take 300
我们将收取您300的学费
in your tuition if you enroll right now.
希望你们会喜欢我所讲的内容
Hope guys you will like me for saying this.
成交
Deal.
顺便说一下
By the way,
在移动设备上工作时
works on the mobile device,
滴滴司机在遇到交通堵塞时
DD driver when they are stuck in traffic
可以去那边和...
can go over there and …
不要在开车的同时
don't drive and (inaudible) at the same time.
就我认为的有关自驾车这个关键问题
Give us a layout of the crucial question
请给我们一个规划
that's in my heart about the self-driving car,
特别是中国在未来扮演的角色
specifically China's role in the future.
好的 在参观了美国之后
Ok. I think China will have a big role
我觉得中国将在自动驾驶上发挥巨大的潜力
in autonomous vehicles when I visited US,
不仅体现在技术上
not necessarily technology,
我发现中国在自动驾驶方面
China is significantly behind,
已经严重落后于美国
in autonomous vehicle technology,
至少要三到五年才能赶上
at least three to five years behind.
我们一定会赶上美国的
We will catch up.
而我认为一个有趣的问题是
And I think the big interesting issue is
如何协调监管 民族 道德
how will the regulatory, ethnical, moral,
环境与自动驾驶之间的关系
environment cause this to take off.
当我去美国的时候
When I go to America,
我的朋友们（不是电脑专业）
my friends, not computer friends
只谈谈两件事情
only want to talk about two things,
一个是有关手摇车的问题
one is the trolley problem,
另一个是自动驾驶在实际操作前
and the second is how good an autonomous vehicle
是怎么的好
has to be before it is allowed to be launched.
这是两个相关的问题
They are related problems,
第一个是从伦理方面来说
the first one is an ethical problem,
比如说你现在独自推着手推车
you now, trolley goes alone, you are driving the trolley
正好前面有一个人
and there is one person ahead of you,
哦 不对 是五个人
sorry, the five people ahead of you,
你可以选择继续前进杀死这五个人
if you don't do anything you kill the five people
或者你可以选择转向
or you could turn and there is one person,
杀死后面的一个人
there you kill one person.
那么你是故意选择主动杀死一个人
So do you purposefully and actively kill one person
还是装作不知道地杀死五个人
or close your eyes and kill five people.
对我来说 答案是不重要的
To me, I thing the answer is unimportant.
我有我的答案
I have my answer,
但我觉得不重要
but I think it is unimportant.
我认为对于这样一个事实
I think it's a fact
美国人似乎在无休止地在辩论
that Americans seem to endlessly want to debate this topic
将技术问题上升到道德上
and turn a technology into a moral problem
这样会阻碍一个国家的发展
that would slow the country down.
我觉得这就像教授们
I think this is like
所研究的哲学问题一样
professors' philosophy problems.
我不喜欢这个问题
I hate the problem.
我会选择杀死一个人
I would choose to kill the one person.
如果你每年
who cares,
能拯救50万人的话 但是谁会在乎呢？
if you save half a million people every year
我知道
I know.
但这种无休止的辩论非常可怕
But this kind of endless debate is terrible.
另一件事是自动驾驶的系统要达到什么程度
The other thing is how good the system has to be.
再次有人强调系统
And again there are people who feel like
一定要贴近完美
it has to be almost perfect,
有些人觉得一定要比
and then people think it has to be
人类操作好得多
absolutely a lot better than human,
有些人又觉得有一点进步就可以了
and then the people think just a little bit better,
我觉得
and I think
在中国可能会有更加务实的讨论
China would probably take the more pragmatic rout.
所以 当科技与人类的同步
so, you think China is going to be breaking ground
而不是略占优势的时候
when the technology gets
你觉得中国会打破常规吗？
as good as the human performance but not better.
我不知道中国每天会发生
I don't know how many accidents kill
多少起死亡事故
people in China everyday,
至少有500？
so at least 500 at least?
也许是1000？
Maybe 1000?
我不知道
I don't know.
在美国 每年有4万人死亡
In the US, there are 40,000 deaths a year,
每天有100人死亡
so 100 people per day.
假设中国的数字是1000
Let's say the number is 1000 in China.
那么使用自驾车就如同每年杀800人
So using self-driving car is like
或一天杀500人一样
killing 800 people's a day or 500 a day.
你说中国更务实 说的很好
You say China is more pragmatic and say it's fine
在中国你将不会遇到太多的交通问题
because you will have less traffic
并且会有更多安静的时间
you have more quiet time than in US
在美国你每天可能会杀死一个人
where you may kill 1 person a day
可能你不会这么做
might not do it.
我不知道中国人会怎样回答这个问题
well, I don't know the answer for China
中国人口稠密
and China has a lot of people and
政府官员众多
many different government officials.
但是我觉得对完美的要求
But I'm saying there will be less obsession
不会这么高
in demanding perfection.
所以这一点
So if it's a bit better than people
不错
maybe it's good enough.
但在美国有这么多的辩论
But in the US there are so much debate.
所有这些辩论都会阻碍美国的发展
US will slow this down with all the debates.
美国的自驾车公司要到中国来吗？
Should self-driving car US company come to China?
我试过了 这非常难！
It's very difficult to come to China. I've tried but.
我在中国有公司
well my company is in China,
是一家自驾汽车公司
we are a self-driving car company now.
我们也要来中国
so should we come to China.
好吧 优达学城来中国
well, Udacity should come to China,
这是一个非常普通的事情
because it's a very universal thing.
对于自驾汽车公司
The self-driving car company
我想你需要一个中国合作伙伴
I think you need a Chinese partner to come in.
所以请跟我谈谈
So please talk to us about
我可能会投资你的公司
maybe investing in your company.
凡事参与美国自驾
the audience involved in
汽车公司的成员
the US self-driving car companies.
如新加坡等国家
There are countries like Singapore
都在极力支持这项技术
which actively encourage this technology.
那不错
that's good.
你觉得他们会这么做吗？
do you think they will leg up?
新加坡确实会这样做
I think Singapore does,
因为这是一项技术
because it's kind of technology
得益于一个控制力良好的
that benefits from a well-controlled
管理环境
and managed environment.
新加坡和中国都是自上而下
Both Singapore and China are relatively
相对制约的管理模式
managed from top down,
新加坡有额外的优势 就是它很小
and Singapore has the additional advantage of being small.
正因为如此才能够控制住
So it's controllable.
所以我觉得新加坡政府鼓励
So I think the Singaporean government actually
创新的方式其实是非常明智的
has been very smart in the way they encourage innovation,
他们通过各种各样的方法
they have various ways to fund
来为创业公司提供资金援助
start up companies with incentives
同时 他们也在开发无人驾驶汽车
and also doing the autonomous vehicle.
他们的治理方式给我留下了深刻的印象
I'm very impressed by their government.
因为你是最成功、最了不起
since you are one of the most amazing entrepreneurs,
最具有远见的企业家、科学家和投资商
amazing scientist, amazing investor,
连我都觉得你是一个传奇
I also think you are an amazing visionary.
可以给我们说说30年后
Tell us something about how technologies
会是什么样的呢？
could be 30 years from now?
你指的是技术还是这个社会？
technology or the world?
都有
both.
对于还在投资期间的一些技术而言
Some technologies, maybe on the investment horizon
这可能是我们的孩子要担心的
but our kids will worry about
他们可能会有更疯狂的举动
and something crazy to do.
我不怎么在乎自己在做什么 我们知道就行
I don't think too much about what I'm doing but we do know.
当你60岁呢？
you will be 60 then.
好吧 我想我还活着
well I think I would be alive,
长寿是 AI 技术
because human longevity is one of the great
最大的成就之一
beneficiary outcomes of AI,
这样的话我们会活得更久
we will live longer.
大部分癌症将会消失
Cancer will be largely eradicated.
到那时我想去哪里就去哪里
So I would be around.
这很重要
That's important.
是我们的目标之一
That's for one.
其实 在接下来的30年里
I think the world actually faces
世界将面临着非常严峻的挑战
very difficult challenging in the next 30 years,
因为AI技术正在取代所有的工作
because AI is taking over all these jobs.
我认为这个结果既好又不好
I think there is a positive negative outcome
因为人们可能会失去努力工作的
that people could lose their incentive to work hard
激情和动力
and lose their motivation.
而且 VR 技术的发展也很好
And also with the VR working so well,
人们只需坐在家里
people could just sit in home
整天玩游戏
and let their brain stop developing
让大脑放松
by playing games all day.
这个结果可能很糟糕
That's possibly one negative outcome.
但我还是比较乐观的
But I think I'm more optimistic
也许还有一个比较好的结果
that maybe a more positive outcome would be
那就是人类再也不需要
that I thing human race was never
去做一些重复的工作
put into place to do just repetitive jobs.
为了追逐金钱和名望
I think we continue to fall into traps
可能还有他人的尊重
because we chase money and fame,
人们可能会继续选择这种生活
Or respect, I should say.
我们的父母告诉我们去当医生 当律师
When our parents tell us, be a doctor, lawyer,
去商学院 做工程师
go to businees school, be an engineer
他们实际上是在和我们说追逐声望和金钱
They are telling us to chase after respect and money.
但是这类工作 很多都会消失
But many of these jobs will be gone.
就好像是造物主在说
So this may be our creator's way to tell us that,
你看 既然你没办法找到自己的人生方向
look, you cannot seem to find your own path,
那我就创造一个 AI
So I'm gonna create an AI to
让你根本没有选择可选
remove those possiblities from your consideration.
你们人类得找到自己的命运和归宿
So you guys, human kinds, need to find your own destiny.
所以我想加入这次大探险
So I'd love to be part of that exploration,
看看这次冒险里 是科学与创造性更加重要
to see whether that's something scientific and creative
还是信仰更加重要
or something that's spiritual and religious,
这就是继无聊的工作之后人类的真实命运
that's the true destiny after the boring jobs are gone,
还是有一些事情值得我们去做
there's something worth our work.
我喜欢这个 因为对我来说
I love this because to me
最值得尊重的人
the people who get the most respect
是那些不听从父母安排、自立自强的人
are the ones who don't follow their parent's advice.
是的
yes.
那些一路疯狂成长的人
the ones who grow something crazy,
比如我 父母不会告诉你如何
like, I don't think your parents have told you
才能成为世界最强的奥赛罗球员
to build the world strongest Othello player,
如何建立世界最强的语音识别系统
build the world strongest speech recognition system
包括你的导师也不会告诉你
and your advisor told you
如何使用专家系统...
to use Expert System…
是的 但我不同意这一点
yes but I didn't.
我的父母出生在20世纪初
But I'm deeply grateful for my parents
我非常感激他们
who were born in the early 1900s,
是他们教我追求梦想
that they let me pursue my dream
选择自己的学校、工作
and let me pick the schools and jobs
事业以及专业
and career and the major.
我真心地感谢他们
I'm deeply grateful for that.
这里有很多你的粉丝 全是年轻人
you have a great audience here, really young people.
如果让你回到年轻时
But if you talked your young self,
比如30岁 25岁
you are 30, 25 years old,
你又会给出什么建议？
what's your advice?
我的建议是跟随你的内心
I would advice follow your heart,
因为这样你才能认清自己
because this is the way how you differentiate yourself.
做和其他人一样的事情
Working on things that everybody else is doing,
你的优势是什么？
what is your edge?
是与其他人及AI技术对着干？
Against other people as well the AI.
还有一件事让我感触很深
The other thing I would say is go very deep,
多台机器同时以五秒的时间
because at the time where five second decisions
重复做功时
are replicated are done by machines,
你必须非常努力地去工作
you have to work hard
才能发现规律
and find the (inaudible) rule
然后为了生存而成为该方面的专家
and really becoming an expert in order to just survive.
开复 很高兴能邀请到你
Kai-fu, I've been, I believe, an honor
并和你畅谈
and pleasure to be with you and ask you questions.
谢谢
Thanks.
和你交谈
Listen to your answer,
感觉我们就像好兄弟一样
it sounds like a brother from a different mother,
老实说 我非常赞同你的所有观点
because I completely agree with whatever you say, honestly.
谢谢你 Sebastian 和你交流也很开心
Thank you Sebastian, always pleasure talking to you,
让我们继续做好哥们
please will continue to call me brother.
当然没问题
Yes.
让我们来宣布最后一条消息
We will make one last announcement.
这里是 Udacity Talk
This is Udacity Talk,
你可以在线观看我们的节目
you can see us online
之前我们也采访过 Tony Fodana
and we have people like Tony Fodana
等人
and interviewed in the past,
我们会采访更多了不起的人物
and we will interview more fascinating people.
这是我们在中国做的第一期节目
This is our first edition outside the US, in China.
每次来中国我都非常高兴
I'm delighted every time I come to China.
因为这个国家取得了很多的成就
I found this country more accomplishments
到处都是企业家 能量
I think you have many entrepreneurs, energy,
创造力 不断推动着你们发展
creativity that blows in your way,
在许多方面你们都创建了一个新的硅谷
I think you are the new Silicon Valley in many ways.
非常荣幸能与开复博士
This's great pleasure to be with Kai-fu,
创新工厂、滴滴等许多公司合作
Sinovation Ventures, DD with many other companies
并向您学习如何建立一个卓越的企业
and learning from you how to build a company.
最后一次
One last time,
如果你喜欢 Udacity 的深度学习课程
if you like this Udacity courses on deep learning,
我们有中文的在线课程 cn.udacity.com
we have courses on line in Chinese, cn.udacity.com,
最近两天报名 会有折扣
for two days if you sign up you get a rebate.
提醒一下 数学上
We recommended you to know
有个自由的模式
there is a liberal pattern in math.
深度学习的特点之一就
One thing about deep learning is
是软件工程师们非常努力
software engineers work really hard,
你必须考虑每一个可能的规则
you have to think every possible rule.
深度学习是一种使之变得容易的方式
Deep learning is a way to make it easy.
只是举个例子 由你来制定规则
You just put example and you make rules.
在计算机程序领域
I think it's an area of computer programing
软件工程师已经过时了
where software engineers are obsolete
拥有非常简单技能的人们
and people with very simple skills can do
可以通过最近在皮肤癌检测
amazing stuff by the recent
的进展中取得惊人的成就
progress on skin cancer detection.
所以 去看看我们的网站
So, go to our website.
我想特别感谢一下李开复博士
I want to thank, specifically Kai-fu Lee of course,
感谢创新工厂、斗鱼直播
his company Sinovation Ventures, Douyu TV,
品玩、机器之心和果壳网MOOC学院
Ping West, Synced and Guokr MOOC
今晚为我们带来的伟大贡献
who was holding us tonight for you contributions.
再次感谢你参与我们的在线访谈
Thank you once more online great questions.
感谢创新工厂的观众
Thank youaudience here in Sinovation Ventures
希望下一次的 Udacity Talks 能继续见到您！
and see you for the next Udacity Talks!
再见！
bye bye